So in מסכת זבחים Masechet Zevachim דף י"ח Daf Yud-Chet
עמוד א' Amud Alef at the top of the page. Yesterday we
started looking at the כהן מחוסר בגדים, Kohen Mechusar Begadim, the כהן
Kohen that is not dressed appropriately in the priestly garments and what
that means for his service. We looked particularly in
two פסוקים. psukim. One is from שמות Shemot כ"ט Kaf-Tet from פרשת
תצוה Parshat Tetzaveh that talks about the clothing of the priests and
one is from ויקרא Vayikra
following the incident of נדב ואביהוא Nadav ve-Avihu that talks about the
כהן Kohen what happens when the כהן Kohen is drunk. We're also
looking at a third place in פרשת כי תשא Parshat Ki Tisa
about washing hands and feet and we're comparing those three פסוקים psukim
for a גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah
where in all of them it says חוק עולם chok olam or
חוקת עולם chukat olam and therefore we learn from one to the
other. All right, we are at אשכחן, Ashkechan, middle of fourth line
from the top on י"ח עמוד א'. yud chet amud aleph
אשכחן מחוסר בגדים שתוי יין מנלן? Ashkechan mechusar begadim shtuyei yayin minalan?
So I found the discussion about מחוסר בגדים, mechusar begadim, this is
where we started and we'll have the whole session about the clothing,
the fashion of the high priest.
And now we're looking at the שתוי יין. shtuyei yayin. We'll see
that there is a lot of back and forth like what are
we learning from
which one are we learning from what and I know Rabbi Linszer
spoke yesterday about the idea of ועבדתם ve-avadtem
והזר הקרב יומת. ve-hazar hakarev yumat. Like ועבדתם ve-avadtem
meaning עבד תם, avad tam, you have to do all the works
and והזר הקרב, ve-hazar hakarev, the non-כהן Kohen would be put to
death,
where we're distinguishing between works of bringing the sacrifice and works that
are like more cleanup and which one applies.
Okay, אתיא חוקה חוקה ממחוסר בגדים והתנא ולהבדיל בין הקודש ובין החול
Atiah chuka chuka mi-mechusar begadim ve-hatana u-lehavdil bein ha-kodesh u-vein ha-chol which
we had in ויקרא. Vayikra. So why do I need all these
פסוקים psukim if I can learn? כנסיב לה מקימי דליקום גזירה שווה.
Kanasiv lah mikimei de-leikum gezeirah shavah. So I learned that before I
had the גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah I had the פסוק, pasuk, but
now that I have the learning of the גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah
then I can use both of them. והתנא מחוסר בגדים הוא דקאליף
משתוי יין. Ve-hatana mechusar begadim hu de-ka-alif mi-shtuyei yayin. So what am
I learning from what? Am I learning the מחוסר בגדים mechusar begadim
from the שתוי יין shtuyei yayin from the כהן Kohen that is
drunk or am I learning it the other way around? הכי קאמר,
Hachi kama, this is how I should learn it. מניין
שלא נחלקו בין מחוסר בגדים לשתוי יין ושלא רחוץ ידים ורגלים תלמוד
לומר חוקה חוקה לגזירה שווה. Minayin she-lo nechelku bein mechusar begadim le-shtuyei
yayin ve-she-lo rachutz yadayim ve-raglayim? Talmud lomar chuka chuka le-gezeirah shavah. So
just like we learn in all of them it's doing the עבודה
avoda in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash wrong is מחלל mechallel all
the עבודות. avodot. So we learn from them to one to the
other that there is no distinction between one that's lacking the appropriate
clothing and those that drink wine and those that have hands and
feet that are not washed, they're all under this חוקה. chuka. So
why do I need the extra פסוקים? psukim? אלא להבדיל למה לי?
Ela lehavdil lama li? Why do I need this שתוי יין? shtuyei
yayin? I have a different דרשה, derasha, I have a story here
about
רב, Rav, לכדרב דדרב לא מוקים אמורא עליה מיום טוב לחבריה משום
שכרות. lichderav de-Rav lo mokim amora aleih mi-yom tov le-chavereih mishum shichrut.
So
רב Rav when he would teach would have a translator, would have
somebody that would explain his words. I find that scene very interesting
that he's teaching and he has a translator.
Which language is he going back and forth from?
But anyway he has a translator. He means like an explicator. Yeah,
like an explainer, right? Somebody that... well that makes sense, that's like
a TA when the professor talks way
over and uses terminology that nobody
understands then. to the next, he would make sure that on יום
טוב *Yom Tov* there's no one next to him so it does
not look like he's teaching הלכה halacha. *halacha* because he's been drinking.
But it's a חיוב *chiyuv* to learn and to teach תורה Torah
*Torah* all times, day or night, יום טוב *Yom Tov*, שבת *Shabbat*.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but also a חיוב *chiyuv* to drink four cups
on
פסח *Pesach*, for example, right? There's אין in, שמחה אלא Ela
בבשר ויין *ein simcha ela bebasar veyayin*, right? So there's other opportunities
where he might have been drinking so he would not have the
translator so it doesn't appear like he's teaching הלכה halacha *halacha*. Lest
חס וחלילה *chas v'chalila* he's speaking when he's drinking. So that's also,
but ironically Charlie it's like he's teaching in action because he's teaching
his students that when you are possibly drinking you should not be
teaching הלכה *halacha*. So that's something that he's teaching. Not just avoiding.
We need to stop giving פורים תורה Torah *Purim Torah* on פורים
*Purim* when we're drunk.
However stop getting drunk. Maybe yeah, maybe as a... Do you know
the saying every exception has an exception except the exception that doesn't
have an exception which is an exception? I've never heard that saying.
Haha. I have. Are you serious? I have. בעברית אומרים לכל כלל
יש יוצא מן הכלל ואם יש כלל שאין לו יוצא מן הכלל
הוא יוצא מן הכלל שלכל כלל יש יוצא מן הכלל *B'Ivrit omrim
lechol klal yesh yotze min haklal v'im yesh klal she'ein lo yotze
min haklal hu yotze min haklal shelechol klal yesh yotze min haklal*.
I hadn't heard the Hebrew version. It's better
in Hebrew. ברוך *Baruch*!
This goes to show how תלמוד *Talmud* trickles into modern Israel. Okay,
all right, all right, all right. Okay so now maybe is this,
is this the right פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from פסוק pasuk *pasuk* ונתתם
לכם *v'netatem lachem*? Maybe there's another פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* in ויקרא Vayikra
*Vayikra* 1:7. So הגמרא *haGemara* is asking, אכתי מהכא נפקא מהתם נפקא
*Akati mehacha nafka mehatam nafka*, ונתנו בני אהרן Aharon, הכהן *v'natnu benei
Aharon haKohen*, and I don't have the full פסוק pasuk *pasuk* and
continue וערכו עצים על האש *ve'archu etzim al ha'esh*. So they're doing
the job of setting the wood on the fire but the
beginning tells us ונתנו בני אהרן הכהן *v'natnu benei Aharon haKohen*. Why
do I need the word הכהן *haKohen*? I already know that the
children of אהרן *Aharon* are a כהן kohen, *Kohen*. There's also thing
about that. That you know right? The sign on top of the
whatever חכמי חלם *Chachmei Chelm* store? No? Yes? Maybe? This is all...
I mean Rabbi Linzer got us a little bit into the דף
*daf* so I cannot... No but there's a famous story that two
whatever חלם *Chelm* guys want to start a business. It's they want
to make a big long sign above the store that says here
we sell fresh fish every day. And then they're like that's a
lot of words. Here? Of course here, we're not sitting there, we're
sitting here. So that's a word we don't know. We sell? Of
course we sell, you can see the fish like we're not buying.
Of course fresh fish, what are we going to sell, rotten fish?
Etc. etc. so we don't need a sign. So here we're doing
something a little bit the same where we're looking at word a
word that is not necessary. We know already that the children of
אהרן *Aharon* are the כהנים Cohanim *Kohanim*. So again it means while
they are wearing their clothing. בכהונו לימד על כהן גדול kohen gadol
שלבש בגדי כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot, ועבד ve’avad, עבודתו פסולה avodato psula.
*Bekihuno limed al Kohen Gadol shelavash bigdei Kohen Hedyot v'avad avodato psulah*.
So what do we learn from the extra statement that בני אהרן
הכהן *benei Aharon haKohen* and we know that the כהונה *kehunah* implies
that they're dressed in their garments? We learn from it that a
כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* who dresses in the garments of
a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot, *Kohen Hedyot* and he did his work
in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*,
his work is פסול pasul, *pasul*. To me the whole,
and I heard some of it yesterday when you guys were learning
of the כהן Kohen *Kohen* wearing the garments right and then he
is a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* and when he's out of his garments
what does it mean he's not a כהן Kohen *Kohen*? So I
think again on my from my experiences of soldiers in the army.
When you are in your uniform you have certain privileges and certain
responsibilities that you don't have when you're not in uniform. Whatever, you
get free rides on the train depends on who's who's in charge
it comes and goes but when you are in your uniform. But
you're still a soldier even if you're not in your uniform and
you went home for vacation you're still in the army. So the
כהנים Cohanim *Kohanim* have Something like that as well, that while they're
on the job, they have to be in the right garments. We'll
see more specifics of the garments
in order to be כשר kasher for the עבודה. avoda. Yes. Yeah,
Rashi quotes that and the note here is that this is actually
a ברייתא braita in תורת כהנים, Torat Cohanim, the ספרא. Sifra. What
do you mean quotes? What we just read. Yes, which would give
that more than just an ordinary גמרא Gemara importance. Okay.
Thank you for adding. Okay. I just looked it up. That's fine.
Okay. אימא התם הוה אמינא הני מילי עבודה דמעכבא כפרה אבל עבודה
דלא מעכבא כפרה לא. Ima hatam hava amina hani mili avoda d'meakva
kapara aval avoda d'lo meakva kapara lo.
So, if we think that this is from the פסוקים psukim we
just see and this is the only thing we would learn, we
would think that it's only
for עבודות avodot that are מעכב כפרה. meakev kapara.
I'm translating it into Hebrew, right? I'm translating Hebrew into Hebrew. Okay.
So like, works in the service in the מקדש Mikdash, that affect
the כפרה, kapara, the atonement. But in something that doesn't affect atonement,
would not be subject to this הלכה. But the
verse that we just quoted in ויקרא Vayikra 1:7
indicates that the הלכה applies even to things that are not מעכב
כפרה. meakev kapara. Okay, let's see another פסוק pasuk right afterwards that
we can learn something else from there. Another פסוק pasuk where the
word כהנים Cohanim might be superfluous, might not be needed. What can
we learn from that? ואכתי מהכא מהתם נפקא. ve'aketi meihacha meihatam nafka.
Next פסוק, pasuk ויקרא vayikra, 1:8, וערכו בני אהרן הכהנים את הנתחים
אשר על המזבח. ve'archu bnei Aharon hacoanim et hanetachim asher al hamizbeach.
So the children of אהרן, the priests, organize the meat on the
altar. Here also, the word כהנים Cohanim not needed. And it comes
to say הכהנים בכהונם. hacohanim bekhonam. We saw this already, that this
means the כהנים kohanim in their garments. מכאן לכהן הדיוט שלבש בגדי
כהן גדול ועבד עבודתו פסולה. mikan lekohen hedyot shelavash bigdei kohen gadol
ve'avad avodato psula.
So also, this goes two ways. One is the כהן גדול kohen
gadol didn't have time to get dressed, wore the minimal clothes of
the כהן הדיוט, went to do his work, פסול, pasul. doesn't count.
Or כהן הדיוט, I don't know, got confused, wore the garments of
the כהן גדול kohen gadol and went to do the worship in
the מקדש, mikdash. עבודתו פסולה. And if we go with my metaphor,
I don't think a high officer can dress up in the, whatever,
basic training kind of soldier and do his work, and that would
be okay. And the other way too, you can't be a startup
soldier in the army and go pretend to be a כהן גדול
kohen gadol and be like, "Hey, look, let me do my job."
Yeah, right. Not working. So we really need both פסוקים
psukim in order to teach each other. Otherwise, we might... okay, here
גמרא Gemara tells us: אימא התם הוה אמינא הני מילי חיסור אבל
ייתור לא קא משמע לן. Ima hatam hava amina hani mili chisur
aval yitur lo ka mashma lan. If we only had one superfluous
place where the word כהנים Kohanim appears, we might think that it's
only when he's מחוסר בגדים, mechussar bgadim, when he's missing some of
his garments. I.e., כהן גדול dressing in the garments of a simple
כהן, that that's a problem. But we wouldn't know that wearing extra
garments is also a problem, and therefore we get both
פסוקים. psukim. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Now we're going to have something
fun. Can I erase anything? Yes, go ahead.
There's a bit of other stuff. That was a great שיעור shiur
yesterday. Huh? This was great yesterday. This whole diagram was great yesterday,
the שיעור shiur about levels of טומאה. tumah. Yeah. Here is what
we have. We're going to see three opinions.
And as I draw, it's going to sound maybe confusing to some,
so here they are on the board: רבנן, Rabanan, שמואל, Shmuel, and
רב. Rav. And we're looking at the garments of the high priest.
Here they are too long and here they are too short.
All right, and we have a question of the belt.
It's going to work.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היו מרושלין מסולקין משוחקין ועבד עבודתו כשירה.
hayu merushalin mesulakin meshuchakin ve'avad avodato k'shera.
Okay,
what do our rabbis... tell us? If the garments of the High
Priest were מרושלין, merushallin, too long, מסולקין, mesullakin, too short, משוחקין, meshuhakin,
worn out or like frayed, ועבד, and he did his work, it’s
kosher. So I am going to put for רבנן rabbanan a smiley.
Yes? Because they say you got to, you got to show the
worn out clothes. How are you going to draw that? I don’t
need them for the discussion, so
or I don’t need them right away. And I’m not doing anything
with the belt. You’ll see, you’ll see, this is just like a
little bit of a spoiler. Okay. לבש שני מכנסיים שני אבנטים חיסר
אחת יתר אחת או שהייתה לו רטייה על מכת בשרו תחת בגדו
או שהיו מטושטשין או מקורעין ועבד עבודתו פסולה. lavash shenei michnasayim shenei
avnetim chisar achat yitar achat o shehayeta lo reti’ah al makat besaro
tachat bigdo o shehayu metushtashin o mekora’in ve’avad avodato pesulah.
So let’s see the qualifications for dressing inappropriately that makes
his עבודה avodah פסול. pasul He wears two pants,
he wears two belts. This reminds me of the people like dress
up to avoid the airport baggage fees. Right, right. Heidi! Heidi plane!
I’ve done that. This, the Heidi
story, that whatever, her family sends her away and dresses her in
everything she’ll need for the next six months. Or refugees trying to
get all their stuff on. Yeah, there’s like serious stories with this.
Yeah. Okay. Two belts, missing one or adding one, or he has
a like a bandage on his flesh under his garment which is
a חציצה, chatzitzah, it’s a separation. And the whole thing is that
in ויקרא, in פרשת צו, parashat tzav, it says in the beginning
of פרשת צו, parashat tzav, it says ולבש הכהן מדו בד. velavash
hakohen mido bad. What is this word מדו? mido?
We don’t know. תהא כמדתו. tehe kemidato.
You should do this. You should do this.
Sorry. Okay, so the garments have to be exactly his מדה,
midah, his size, right? Okay. או שהיו מטושטשין o shehayu metushtashin and
they say מטושטשין, metushtashin, רש״י rashi says בטיט. betit. Soiled with dirt.
Or מקורעין, mekora’in,
torn. רש״י rashi says ואפילו אינן חדשים, ve’afilu einan chadashim, דלאו בגדו
הראוי לעבודה דבעינן לכבוד ולתפארת. delav bigdo hara’ui la’avodah dabe’inan lechavod uletiferet.
So this is a whole question around the כהנים kohanim and hopefully
we’ll get even to the top of the next page and see
maybe how that speaks to us. Interestingly the worn away isn’t considered
to be not be, you know, the frayed. The משוחק. meshuhak. משוחק
meshuhak is it’s like you know it became a little threadbare but
it’s intact. But that’s okay. Yes. And I mean was there an
aspect of reality? Like the whole thing of how did they make
these garments? These were like
this was before mass factories, right? And like they had to spin
everything and make everything from scratch. And maybe there was some reality
of you couldn’t get the flax and you couldn’t get the material
and you still had need to go to the מקדש. Mikdash So
we’re working with it. Okay, so we have our list. Talked with
each other or everybody had their own? Oh, I don't know, Michael
do you know? That’s a good question. I don't think I’ve ever
seen a reference to that. Although in the כהן גדול he was
definitely, you need women in the גמרא. gemara. I
think they had cubbyholes at the sanctuary.
So each one had his own. And also because he could sleep,
when they slept they could roll it up under their head. Yeah,
yeah, not usually, so that they would wear it and take it
off when they’re not on duty.
Or until they got too old or whatever, like you know, give
it back to the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. I don't remember. Didn’t
they use also some of the old garments for the fifteen? They
use them for the fifteen celebrations on the בית המקדש beit hamikdash
for the wicks and stuff? Right. And the יום כיפור yom kippur
garments were not reused.
Right. Amazing.
Okay. Alright. So
we have our list of what כשר kasher according to the rabbis
and the list of what’s not כשר kasher, and we'll need it
as we proceed. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מרושלין כשרים מסולקין פסולים.
amar rav yehuda amar shmuel merushallin kesherin mesullakin pesulin. והתניא מסולקין כשרים.
vehatanya mesullakin kesherin. Right?
So smileys, where’s my pen?
What does שמואל shmuel say? מרושל merushal which is long, מרושל, merushal,
מסולק, mesullak,
right? This is long and this is short. So the מרושל merushal
for שמואל shmuel is כשר, kasher. but the מסולק mesullak is not.
גמרא gemara immediately asking, but what? We have a תניא tanya that
says the מסולק mesullak is כשר. kasher. אמר רמי בר חמא לא
קשיא. amar rami bar chama lo kashya. No problem. כאן שסילקן על
ידי אבנט כאן דליטין נפיש. kan shesilkann al yedei avnet kan delitin
nafish.
So, how do we make the מסולק mesulak. *mesulak* כשר kasher. *kosher*?
It has a belt. If it doesn't have a belt, then indeed
it's too short, but it has a belt. It pulls it up
a little bit. Okay, but isn't the belt one of the... Yeah,
but yes. So, but what do you do with the belt? Bunch
it up a little with the belt. So it's not just a...
the belt actually has a purpose beyond being simply a... Yes, so
the belt can be just on the body or you can be
like taking it out a little bit and putting it over the
belt.
I didn't do a
show and tell. Okay, you didn't wear a belt today? Huh? I
didn't wear a belt. There's a note just a few pages earlier
that let us speak relative to all this. It's from
ויקרא *Vayikra* 6:3 says the כהן *kohen* shall don his fitted linen
tunic. Oh, I didn't catch that. Okay, yeah, yeah, thanks.
But if it's short and you wear a belt, doesn't that make
it shorter? Yeah, exactly. But רגע rega, רגע רגע *rega rega rega*,
that's what שמואל *Shmuel's* saying. They're inherently the right length, it's just
that right now you're walking around with them bunched up with your
belt, so now it's too short on you. We're going to have
a long discussion about this, hence the chart.
A long discussion, but with a belt it's going to get shorter.
Not too long and not too short, just right. Okay, but the
כהן *kohen*... yeah,
it's nice to hear this discussed about other than women's skirt lengths
in this context.
Not commenting.
The כהן *kohen's* garments have to be just right. But what if
not? Like, who made them the clothes, right? How was it measured?
The custom tailor did it, made it to measure them. Okay, so
now you gain weight, you lose weight, it was a good year,
a bad year. That would imply they have to be individual. No,
but also like, you grow, I mean, you know. They didn't really
allow anyone less than 20 to actually do it, although from 13
on, but who knows, you know. But like things happen. Okay, so
the belt has a... is both part of the garment and has
a purpose. Okay. רב Rav, אמר *Rav amar* אחד זה ואחד זה
פסולים *echad zeh ve-echad zeh psulim*. Ah, רב Rav,
*Rav* says, forget it. If it doesn't fit, I think it's פסול
pasul. *pasul*. So you can imagine we're going to have a long
discussion about this, which makes sense, I mean, if we're saying all
these other things are פסול pasul. *pasul* because it's not כבוד ותפארת
*kavod ve-tifaret*. Exactly
the whole thing. Now, what the
overview before we read בפנים *bifnim*, what the... the רבנן Rabbanan? *Rabanan*
don't tell us the status of what we can do with the
belt, right? They didn't say anything. They just said מרושלים *merushalim* or
מסולק *mesulak*, it's fine. We can work with it. They didn't tell
us the parameters.
Who was it there? רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* solves שמואל
*Shmuel's* issue by either reminding us or telling us that this is
with a belt. Like when the cloth is not there and it's
too short, it's פסול pasul. *pasul*. But when the cloth is there
and it's only short because of a belt. Also another situation, for
example, the כהן *kohen* goes to work,
his garments are... they fit just right, but whatever, he bent, moved,
something, it got caught and now it's shorter. Okay, now he walks
out and he's like, oops,
it was shorter. Is the whole עבודה *avoda* פסול *pasul* because the
clothing was not just right? Or it's like, no, it was just
מסולק *mesulak* because of a belt. So can it be בדיעבד bedieved
*be-di'avad*
okay? Because לכתחילה *le-chat'chila* it should be that they go with the
right thing. Okay, so רב *Rav* tells us, and where's רש"י *Rashi*?
רש"י *Rashi* says on רב *Rav*, אחד מרושל merushal, ואחד מסולקים mesulakim
יותר מדי שלא על ידי אבנט avnet, *echad merushal ve-echad mesulakim yoter
midai she-lo al yedei avnet*. So no belt, it doesn't fit, פסול
*pasul*. Okay, story. רב הונא *Rav Huna* איקלע לארגיזא *ikl'a le-Argiza*, רב
הונא *Rav Huna* chanced upon a place called ארגיזא *Argiza*. I'd love
to hear more commentary about it if somebody has, because רוגז *rogez*
means anger, so ארגז
*argaz*?
Like a box? Okay, maybe. All right, leave it. רמא ליה בר
אושפיזכניה *Rama lei bar ushpizkaniya*, like the son of his host asked
him a difficult question. Okay, מי אמר שמואל מרושלין merushlin? כשרין ומסולקין
פסולין והתניא מסולקין כשרין *Mi amar Shmuel merushalin kesherin u-mesulakin psulin ve-hatanya
mesulakin kesherin*? Like, who's the one that said this, that שמואל *Shmuel*
said that the long is okay and the short is פסול *pasul*,
and we have a תניא tanya *Tanya* that the short is כשר
kasher, *kasher*? אמר לו בר מינה *Amar lo bar mina*. He said
to him basically... Leave us alone.
דהא דשניא רמי בר חנא. Rami bar Chana, This already was resolved
by רמי בר חנא, don't touch it.
We're not going back into this. But really we don't get into
something. אלא לרב קשיא. leRav kashya. וכי תימא, Vechi teima, ואם תאמר,
veim tomar, מאי mai מרושלין? מסולקים על ידי אבנט, mesulakim al yedei
avnet, ואבנט מכסא גזיז. veavnet mikasa gaziz. Okay,
so with רב, that is more of a difficulty because he thinks
that they're dragging both when they're... that they're פסול both when they're
dragging, when they're too long.
And if you would say, what is this dragging business in the
ברייתא, braita, right, with the רבנן?
It means that it initially was too long, but then it was
raised up by the belt, and the belt makes it like it's...
it's like trims it. Okay, but the מסולקים is still כשר. So
we can explain these with the belt. Okay, so the belt here
helps us adjust. If I don't need to make it too short,
the belt just sits. If I need to make it fit, then
the belt can help me fit. But what do they do with
the too short, like if it doesn't have... if it doesn't have
enough material? What do I do with that? Let me see my
notes. Okay. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, רב חד תני. Rav
chad tani. He says the same thing. He says the same thing
as the... okay,
just a
second. He says חד תני chad tani says one thing: מרושלין שסילקן
על ידי אבנט כשרים. merushlin shesilkan al yedei avnet kesherim. Still agreeing
that
the מרושל, the too long, that was adjusted with the belt is
כשר.
Let me see the רש״י Rashi on this side. It says:
ומסולקים גבוהים מן הקרקע למעלה מרגליו משמע, ולרב ליכא לאוקמה כגון שסילקן
על ידי אבנט. Umesulakim gevohim min hakarka lemala meraglav mashma, uleRav leka
leokma kegon shesilkan al yedei avnet. So we still... we still left
with that question. Is it... what is the place of the belt?
For sure we know there's a place for the belt here in
settling
שמואל׳ס Shmuel's understanding. There might be a belt here that we don't
know about where the sages just say: it just needs to fit,
make... make it fit.
And for רב, we can assume that this would work, not sure
what to do with the
מסולק. Okay.
I think according... with my example that I brought that if he
works in the מקדש and then he discovers that the garments were
caught in the belt, it could be פסול.
Okay.
I see. אמר רב ירמיה מדיפתי, Amar Rav Yirmeya miDifti, מרושלין שלא
סילקן תנאי היא. merushlin shelo silkan tannai hi. So now we have...
we're going to bring sort of a proof, or we're going to
bring another conversation into this where we're going to try to learn
about the garments of the כהנים from ציצית tzitzit and see if
that can help us to know whether it needs to be fit
or it can be adjusted.
Okay, so this is the dispute. Can you raise it and adjust
it or does it have to be just right? And we're going
to look at two ways to read two פסוקים pesukim about ציצית.
tzitzit.
Okay. דתניא. Detanya. In דברים... Devarim...
דברים Devarim 22, it says: על ארבע כנפות כסותך אשר תכסה בה
גדילים תעשה לך. Al arba kanfot kesutcha asher techaseh bah gedilim taaseh
lach. So you're going to have ציציות tzitziyot on the four corners
of your garment which with which you will cover yourself.
Okay, so now what does it mean? There is a ריבוי, ribui,
there is an expansion of the פסוק pasuk, because it says everything
that covers you. Okay, but it also initially says on the four
corners of your garment. So which way is it? Is it on
the four corners or is it on everything that covers you? So
the first ברייתא, braita, the first תניא tanya says: ארבע ולא שלוש,
או אינו אלא ארבע ולא חמש? Arba velo shalosh, o eino ela
arba velo chamesh? What is this term four corners is trying to
tell us? That it's four and not three, or four and not
five?
When he
says... So there'll be two opinions as
surprisingly, right? There'll be two opinions. Okay, כשהוא אומר kshehu omer אשר
תכסה בה asher techase bah הרי בעלת חמש עמו. harei ba'alat chamesh
imo. It's like, okay, if you say
anything that covers yourself needs ציצית, tzitzit, right? This term אשר תכסה
בה, asher techase bah, anything should be anything, right? Okay, so this
comes לרבות, lerabot, oh five needs to. הא מה אני מקיים ha
ma ani mekayem ארבע, arba, so while I have five I have
also four, ארבע ולא שלוש, arba velo shalosh, so
if a garment is bigger I need ציצית, tzitzit, I still need
ציצית tzitzit on it even if it has five corners. Okay, ומה
ראית לרבות בעלת חמש ולהוציא בעלת שלוש, uma ra'ita lerabot ba'alat chamesh
ulehotzi ba'alat shalosh, maybe it's maybe it's backwards, maybe it tells us
exactly what Michael's saying, that it comes to
להוציא את השלוש. lehotzi et hashalosh. מרבה אני בעלת חמש שיש בכלל
חמש ארבע. marbe ani ba'alat chamesh sheyesh bichlal chamesh arba. I can
say five because five also includes four, ומוציא אני בעלת שלוש שאין
בכלל שלוש ארבע. umotzi ani ba'alat shalosh she'ein bichlal shalosh arba. So
it's better for me to make a ריבוי ribuy and include everybody,
but if I only say three, three doesn't include four, but five
includes everything.
איזה יופי. eize yofi. Okay, now what's the other the other option
is to see it
backwards. So one option is anything that you cover yourself with אשר
תכסה בה asher techase bah needs גדילים, gedilim, and the other option
is it's it comes to minimize and exclude only something that has
four corners needs to have the ציצית. tzitzit. Okay,
תניא אידך tanya idach על ארבע כנפות כסותך al arba kanfot k'sutecha
ארבע ולא שלוש ארבע ולא חמש. arba velo shalosh arba velo chamesh.
Only four, not more and not less. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי. mai
lav beha kamiflagi. What is it that the נקודת מחלוקת nekudat machloket
is? דמר סבר יתר כמאן דאיתא דמי ומר סבר כמאן דליתא דמי.
demar savar yeter keman de'ita dami umar savar keman deleita dami. One
thinks that, okay, one thinks that a garment with five corners does
not need a ציצית tzitzit because this is not the garment that
the Torah spoke of. It only spoke of a garment that has
four corners. If it has four corners put a ציצית, tzitzit, if
it doesn't, that's not what we're talking about. The other opinion thinks
five garments includes the four and therefore I ignore the fifth and
I still have to put a ציצית tzitzit on that garment because
I see that there is four including in the five. Yes, kind
of? Okay, okay. All
right, so now we'll see that we actually can learn other things
also from these פסוקים psukim and the גמרא gemara rejects this. לא
lo דכולי עלמא יתר כמאן דאיתא דמי. dekulei alma yeter keman de'ita
dami. So like
you can't say that if there's something there it's not there. I.e.
if there's five corners you can't say there's no five corners there.
And from there we learn for the כהנים that if something is
dragging, it's too much, right, like five corners, you can't say that
it's not there. It's still it's still
not not fit, still פסול. Okay, ושאני הכא דריבי רחמנא אשר תכסה
בה, v'shani hacha d'ribi rachmana asher techase bah, so why why do
we have this ריבוי? ribuy?
There's a different lesson that we can
learn from the ריבוי ribuy that says אשר תכסה בה, asher techase
bah, with which you cover yourself. ואידך האי אשר תכסה בה מאי
עביד ליה, ve'idach hai asher techase bah mai avid leh, what are
we what are we learning? מיבעי ליה כדתניא. mibaye leh kidtanya.
We're bringing another פסוק pasuk that talks about ציצית tzitzit which is
the פסוק pasuk, we read every day from במדבר bamidbar 15, וראיתם
אותו והיה לכם לציצית. ure'item oto vehaya lachem letzitzit. And now we're
gonna learn from that
something else about the ציצית tzitzit which I think we're familiar with.
פרט לכסות לילה, prat lichsut laila, right, או אינו פרט לכסות סומא.
o eino prat lichsut suma. So what do we know about the
ציצית? tzitzit? Because it says וראיתם, ure'item, because we need to see
it, this could exclude night clothing when we can't see,
or clothing of a סומא suma person who can't see, right?
Okay, but כשהוא אומר kshehu omer אשר תכסה בה, asher techase bah,
the garment with which you cover yourself, הרי כסות סומא עמו, harei
k'sut suma imo, it does obligate the blind person. והא מה אני
מקיים וראיתם. veha ma ani mekayem ure'item. I can, how do I
know which to include and which to exclude? I include the blind
person and I exclude the night. I make the night my my
מיעוט miut because we have to see it. So this makes it
a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא. mitzvot aseh she'hazman grama. What? The ציצית.
tzitzit. Yeah, because it's in the daytime only when you can see
it. רגע, yes. Yes. But it is only when you see it.
But we can also make... גמרא Gemara is asking, what about the
opposite?
ומה ראית u'ma raita לרבות כסות סומא lerabot kesut suma ולהוציא כסות
לילה. ule'hotzi kesut laila.
Maybe I can include the garments of the blind person and exclude
the
night garments and not the other way around? מרבה אני כסות סומא
marbeh ani kesut suma שישנה בראיה אצל אחרים sheyeshna bere'iya etzel acherim
ומוציא אני כסות לילה umotzi ani kesut laila שאינה בראיה אצל אחרים.
she'eina bere'iya etzel acherim. Okay. So I include the garments of the
blind person and I exclude the night clothing. Why? Because the blind
person, even though he may not be able to see it, others
can see his clothing
while at night nobody can see nobody can see nobody can see
what somebody is wearing. It's not visible to themselves and to others.
Is that because of nighttime or because of modesty? I think because
it's dark, because it's a visibility thing. But if somebody has something
else some... here...
this is my understanding that it has to do with וראיתם אותם.
u'reitem otam.
Hence the question about the blind person who can't see the וראיתם,
reitem, but at night nobody can see.
In the day, at least other people can see. Is that that
you're wearing it not as inner garments but as outer garments?
The ציצית. tzitzit. Yeah. Yeah, also or the גדילים. gedilim. The strings,
yeah. Okay.
And we'll see that the two opinions: ואידך נפקא ליה מאשר. ve'idach
nafka lei me'asher. So one sage at this word in the פסוק
pasuk that we looked in דברים Devarim that says אשר תכסה בה,
asher techaseh ba, one person looks at the word אשר asher and
makes a דרשה drasha on it, right? Derives that the five-cornered garment
still requires the גדילים, gedilim, right? And the other one... Does אשר
asher teach you anything? Huh? How does אשר asher teach you anything?
Maybe you don't need it? Let's see. Let's look at the full
full פסוק, pasuk? right? על ארבע כנפות כסותך. al arba kanfot kesutecha.
I mean, you see both opinions. You can have the word אשר
asher as like 'what do I need it?' You could say it
maybe differently. על ארבע כנפות כסותך אשר תכסה בה. al arba kanfot
kesutecha asher techaseh ba. But the נו בסדר, nu beseder, it's
אשר. asher. Then it's using an אשר. asher. I'm sure the תורה
Torah could do something better than me on this spot. על
ארבע כנפות כסותך תכסה בה. al arba kanfot kesutecha techaseh ba.
Maybe.
You can't ask me to rewrite the תורה Torah on my on
the spot. And
but you can see both opinions, right? One says מאשר me'asher I
can get something out of it and one says אשר לא דריש,
asher lo darish, doesn't think that this word אשר asher is an
extra word, like your opinion, and therefore doesn't think that a דרש
drash needs to be made on it. Okay. I see that one
over there doesn't make any sense to me.
Which one? So
you want to share? Yeah, there's a debate about the nature of
what a night garment is. Okay. Yeah, that's in another גמרא Gemara
somewhere. We'll get to it. Yes, and רמב"ם וראש ור"ן. Rambam ve'Rosh
ve'Ran.
Yes, based on a גמרא. Gemara. Like they in the question of
if somebody wears his pajamas in the day, right? Do they need...
exactly. Yes. So I think I made a note somewhere that the
ר"ן Ran says that a night garment is exempt from ציצית tzitzit
even in the day. Okay.
Let's continue. So we have another another question about our clothing.
תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: בד bad
שיהיו של בוץ, sheyihyu shel butz, בד bad שיהיו חדשים, sheyihyu chadashim,
בד bad שיהיו שזורים, sheyihyu shezurim, בד bad שיהיו חוטן כפול שישה,
sheyihyu chutan kaful shisha, בד bad שלא ילבש חול עמהם. shelo yilbash
chol imahem. So it says about the כהן that he is going
to wear. בד, bad, right? Like the material he is wearing is
linen.
And the word בד bad repeats in the תורה Torah, seven times,
at least. Some say more. Once in תצוה, Tetzaveh, twice in צו,
Tzav, in פרשת צו, Parshat Tzav, and four times in אחרי מות,
Acharei Mot, which we just read. So what are all the different
things that we can learn from this word בד? bad?
It should be בוץ, butz, fine linen. It should be new. It
should be woven,
not single thread. It should be times six, whether that's the one
to seven, and it should not, he should not wear, he should
not wear חול chol clothes, like mundane clothes with it, or non-sacred.
Interesting because the that belt of the כהן, even the simple כהן
is made from שעטנז. shatnez. So not everything is made out of
linen, but the but the shirt, the tunic and the pants are
בד. bad. Okay. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף: Amar lei Abaye l'Rav
Yosef: בשלמא שיהיו של בוץ הא קמשמע לן. Bishlama she'yihyu shel butz,
ha kamashmalan. So
we're going to
learn more about their garments. Okay. בוץ butz אין, in, מדיא אחרינא
לא. midaya acharana lo. The it should be fine linen is yes,
is כשר, and something else and some other material is not. אלא
בד שיהיו חדשים. Ella bad she'yihyu chadashim. חדשים chadashim אין, שחוקים לא.
shchukan lo. והתניא משוחקים כשרים. Ve-tanya meshuchakim kesherim.
Here we're told the garments have to be new.
Yes new, no worn out. Worn out will be פסול. But we
had a תניא if you remember forty minutes ago at the bottom
of יח Yud-Chet עמוד א Amud Alef. where we had this whole
long list that we said we're going to keep in mind for
four lines from the bottom on יח א. yud chet aleph. תנו
רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: היו מרושלים מסולקים משוחקים ועבד עבודתו כשרה. Hayu merushalaim
mesulakim meshuchakim ve'avad avodato keshera. And now we're told not. So
let's let's see, let's see what we do with it. אמר ליה:
Amar lei: ולטעמיך, u'letameich, בד שיהיו חוטן כפול ששה, bad she'yihyu chutan
kaful shisha, בד חד לחודיה משמע. bad chad l'chudai mashma. Okay, so
the definition of בד, bad, think about another Hebrew word,
hopefully connected,
לבד, levad, בדד. badad. It's a single thread. It's a single stalk
of the flax plant. It's it's alone.
And this is what it says. בד בד חד חד לחודיה משמע.
Bad bad chad chad l'chudai mashma. But the thread has to be
שזור, shazur, has to be not a single, each one of them
is a single thread but they have to be woven together. Okay.
אלא הכי קאמר: Ella hachi ka'amar: בגדים שנאמר בהן בד צריכין שיהיו
של בוץ חדשים שזורים שיהיה חוטן כפול שש. Begadim shene'emar bahen bad
tzrichim she'yihyu shel butz chadashim shezurim she'yehei chutan kaful shesh. יש מהן
למצוה ויש מהן לעכב. Yesh me'hen l'mitzvah ve'yesh me'hen l'akev. What the
what
this ברייתא braita is saying that we just saw at the top
of the תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan,
where it says linen, where it says about the garments linen, it
must be made from fine linen, it must be new, it must
be twisted, and it must be folded six times. And some of
these
requirements will constitute
things that are you know בדיעבד would be okay and some of
them would be things that might be מעכב me'akev the work.
Okay. ממאי דהאי בד כותנא הוא? Mimmai d'hai bad kutnah hu? How
do we know that this term בד, bad, right, that keeps like
referencing itself, how do we know that that has to be from
the flax plant? We don't have right? It just says בד. bad.
How do we know it's not it's got to be not something
made from something else? אמר רבי יוסף ברבי חנינא: Amar Rabbi Yosef
b'Rabbi Chanina: דבר העולה מן הקרקע בד בבד. Davar ha'oleh min ha'karka
bad b'vad. We're talking about a stalk that grows from the ground,
each stalk in its own, בד בבד, bad b'vad, alone, and something
that does not split into multiple stalks. And flax
does that naturally. Yes, fulfills that criteria. But the term in the
תורה Torah is שש. shesh. שש משזר, shesh moshzar, six. Six.
I mean the to referring to the to the linen. Yes. But
and they're not even mentioning that. Why?
They're just saying, and we, like Michael said, we might meet it
somewhere else in מנחות Menachot or in other places where we're going
to talk, where we're going to talk about it again. We're
just from the fact that the word בד bad repeats so many
times in the תורה, but it doesn't tell us, it tells us
the qualities of what this cloth is going to become, but doesn't
tell us what's the origin, what's the material we made it from.
So the גמרא Gemara is asking אימא עמרא, eima amra, maybe wool?
Maybe that should be wool? עמרא מפצל, amra miftzal, wool doesn't fulfill
this criteria, it splits. So it's not a בד בד, bad bad,
it's not a single.
And then גמרא Gemara is asking כיתנא נמי מפצל, kitna nami miftzal,
maybe the flax also splits? על ידי לקותא מפציל, al yedei lakuta
miftzil, but it only, it only
splits when you hit it, when it gets whacked. Not naturally. רבינא
אמר מהכא, Ravina amar meihacha, where do we learn this, what is
the source of this בד bad business? From יחזקאל. Yechezkel. פארי פשתים
יהיו על ראשם ומכנסי פשתים יהיו על מתניהם ולא יחגרו ביזע. pe'erei
pishtim yihyu al rosham umichnesei pishtim yihyu al motneihem velo yachgeru beyaza.
We're going to need this פסוק in the next paragraph, in this
upcoming paragraph from יחזקאל Yechezkel 44:18.
They shall wear פשתים pishtim linen crowns upon their heads and they
will have linen pants on their waist and they will not gird
themselves with יזע. yaza. יזע yaza is close to the word זיעה,
zeia, sweat. And so we're going to see what we learn from
it, but let's just leave it. And the פשתים, pishtim, פשתים pishtim
is clearly flax. We know that פשתים pishtim is flax. Okay. אמר
ליה רב אשי לרבינא: amar lei Rav Ashi le-Ravina: והא עד דאתא
יחזקאל מנלן? ve-ha ad de-ata Yechezkel minalan? Okay, this
is good, right?
יחזקאל Yechezkel shows up after
480 years of משכן mishkan and the beginning of the first temple,
and מוקדם ומאוחר, mukdam u-meuchar, huh? And
800 years after במדבר Bamidbar or whatever. Okay. ולטעמיך הא דאמר רב
חסדא, ule-tameich ha de-amar Rav Chisda,
and we're going to learn this later in our מסכת, masechet, דבר
זה מתורת משה רבינו לא למדנו מדברי יחזקאל בן בוזי למדנו. davar
ze mitorat Moshe Rabbeinu lo lamadnu midivrei Yechezkel ben Buzi lamadnu. So
we don't have that anywhere in the תורה where it says that
the בד bad is the flax.
We get it from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. And we have a פסוק, כל
בן נכר ערל לב וערל בשר לא יבוא אל מקדשי לשרתני. kol
ben nechar arel lev ve-arel basar lo yavo el mikdashi lesharten-ni.
So in the same context, it says everyone who is a stranger,
foreigner, whether he has an uncircumcised heart, i.e., not intended, or physically
uncircumcised in his flesh, cannot come to my sanctuary. And we ask
again, עד דבא יחזקאל מנלן, ad deba Yechezkel minalan, until יחזקאל Yechezkel
came, what did we do with it? אלא גמרא גמירי לה. ela
gemara gemiri lei. We just knew it. This is when my daughter
was three and I asked her how do you know to make
חלה, challah, how to make חלה? challah? She said, I just know.
So this is what they say, we had a מסורת. masoret. ואתא
יחזקאל ואסמכיה אקרא. ve-ata Yechezkel ve-asmachei akra. So יחזקאל Yechezkel came and
gave us a פסוק for later generations so we know what the
practice was before, but not because the practice began then and not
because he's teaching us something from scratch. He's just validating something that
was done and was known. מאי, mai, what about the rest of
the פסוק? ולא יחגרו ביזע, ve-lo yachgeru be-yaza, that they will not
gird themselves with sweat kind of, what are we making of that?
אמר אביי: amar Abaye: לא יחגרו במקום שמזיעין. lo yachgeru bemakom she-mazi'in.
Don't put the belt, the garment, the belt, the אבנט, in
the place where a person sweats. כדתניא: kidetanya: כשהם חוגרים, keshe-hem chogrim,
when they gird themselves with the with the belt, אין חוגרים לא
למטה ממתניהם ולא למעלה מאציליהם. ein chogrim lo lemata mimotneihem velo lemala
me'atzileihem. Don't put it higher from the waist and not lower from
where the elbow's height is, because those are places in the body
where there might be folds of flesh and then there's going to
be sweat and it's going to be inappropriate. אלא כנגד אצילי ידיהם,
ela keneged atzilei yedeihem,
opposite their elbows. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, אמר לי הונא
בר נתן, amar li Huna bar Natan, and I'll finish with this
story because it's just a good closure for this whole conversation. זימנא
חדא, zimna chada, once upon a time... once upon a time הוה
קאימנא קמיה דאיזגדר *hava kaimna kamei de'izgadar* איזגדר מלכא *izgadar malka*. So
once upon a time I was standing before איזגדר *Izgadar*, איזגדר *Izgadar*
yes, the Persian king, והוה מיטלי לי המייני *ve'hava mitlei li hemyani*
like my belt was not quite sitting right and תרציה ניהליה *tirtzeih
nihaleih* he like,
he fixed it, he fixed my belt right on me. This is
not, I mean he's in front of the Persian king, not necessarily
in המקדש *Hamikdash*, just like you know my garment was not sitting
right and so he fixed it for me and he said to
me ואמר לי *v'amar li* don't you like it when the Persian
king reminds us who we are?
He said from שמות *Shemot* 19 before מתן תורה *matan torah* ממלכת
כהנים וגוי קדוש *mamlechet kohanim vegoy kadosh* כתיב בכו *ktiv bechu*. It
says about you, not just the כהנים *Kohanim* are כהנים *Kohanim* and
have all these instructions, which clearly the Persian king knew, and only
the כהנים *Kohanim* have the instructions on how to dress, you yourself
are ממלכת כהנים *mamlechet kohanim*, you are a priestly nation and a
גוי קדוש *goy kadosh* and a holy people, this is what it
says about you. כי אתאי קמיה דאמימר *ki atay kamei d'Amemar* when
I came with this, says רב אשי *Rav Ashi* in this, says
הונא בר נתן *Huna bar Natan* telling רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, when
I came before אמימר *Amemar* and I told him this story, he
said to me אמר לי *amar li* אקיים בך *akayem becha* fulfilled
in you a פסוק *pasuk* from ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* 49 והיו מלכים אומניך
*vehayu melachim omnecha*. Kings will be like your foster parents, kings will
teach you תורה *Torah* and how you need to be. So Rabbi
Steinsaltz points out that הונא בר נתן *Huna bar Natan* was the
ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta* at the time of אמימר *Amemar* and רב
אשי *Rav Ashi*. Good. So, some thoughts about you know who we
are and how we should wear ourselves, wear our clothes and present
ourselves in public and with that a wonderful day. יישר כוח *Yasher
koach*. Thank you.